A Guide to the Carl Van Vechten-Mark Lutz Collection,
Rare Books and Special Collections, Boatwright Library, University of Richmond
- Gertrude Stein Materials
  - Two consecutive issues of Real America: The Out-spoken Magazine, Vol. 6, Nos. 4 & 5 (January, February, 1936). 1936 (Box 10:8)
    Both of these carry articles about Gertrude Stein. January's has a piece by Lucille Hecht entitled: " Gertrude Stein's Magnificent Hoax," on pp. 8-11, & 70. While February's issue has a second by the same reporter called: "Gertrude Stein's Conquest of the Mid West." pp. 43, & 76-77 feature a much more ambitious article, entitled: "James Joyce and Gertrude Stein: A Well Known Literary Critic Gives His Impressions of Modernistic Authors." Harry Beardsley is the "Well Known Literary Critic" whose "Impressions" well and truly slam Stein's style and grammar, whilst jolly Jim Joyce garners all the plaudits.
  - Left hand side-from last entry-(a continuation.)
  - Harper's Magazine, Vol. 195, Serial No. 1171 (December 1947). pp. 519-528, an article by Katherine Anne Porter entitled: "Gertrude Stein: A Self-Portrait." 1947 (Box 10:9)
  - Academic Observer, Utica, New York, Vol. LI, No. 4 (February, 1937). 1937 (Box 10:10)
    "Gertrude Stein Number." p. 4, "Gertrude Stein," by Associate Editor Margaret Lucha. Opposite on p. 5 is a Facsimile of a letter written her by Gertrude Stein-undated.
  - The Choate Literary Magazine, Vol. XXI, No. 2 (February, 1935). 1935 (Box 10:*11)
    "How Writing is Written," by The Woman Herself-the text of a Lecture delivered the previous month under the auspices of the above magazine, pp. 5-14. Inscribed: *"For Mark ["Illegible"] [Signed] "Gtde."
  - Letters: A Quarterly of Unpublished Letters and other Belles Lettres, 1935 (Box 10:12)
    No. 1 (Spring 1935). [pp. 16-17 pages are not numbered]. On the one hand is a facsimile of Stein's handwriting; on the other "Gertrude Stein to Cousins in Baltimore." No date.
  - The Reviewer, Vol. IV, No. 3 (April 1924). *Published in Richmond, VA. 1924 (Box 10:**13)
    Founded and edited by Emily Clark and Hunter Stagg. Table of Contents on the cover, beside which the inimitable Gertrude wrote: *"To Mark and Carl [illegible] is for both of them with much pleasure. Gtde." The article by Gertrude Stein is "Van or Twenty Years After: A Second Portrait of Carl Van Vechten" pp. 176-177.
  - Books Abroad: An International Quarterly 1939 (Box 10:14)
    Vol. 13, No. 3 (Summer 1939). pp. 306-308, "My Debt to Books," a composite article by Roda Roda and Gertrude Stein, separate and distinct, but under a common heading.
  - An Exhibition: Pictures for a Picture of Gertrude Stein as a Collector and Writer On Art and Artists. 1951 (Box 10:15)
    Yale University Art Gallery, February 11-March 6, 1951, and The Baltimore Museum of Art, March 21-April 21, 1951.
  - M.S.S. 1940 (Box 10:16)
    A Publication of The Scroll and Stylus Club of Stockton Junior College and the College Of the Pacific, 1940. pp. "Is Dead," a Story by Gertrude Stein.
  - The Flowers of Friendship: Letters written to Gertrude Stein. 1953 (Box 10:*17)
    Edited by Donald Gallup. New York: Alfred A Knopf, Publisher, 1953. Publisher's Pamphlet. Inscribed: *"For Marko only From Carlo Always June 11, 1953."
  - Bibliographer of Gertrude Stein (Box 10:18)
    Photocopies of acid-eroded typescript.
- Gertrude Stein Pamphlets
  - Gertrude Stein: Catalogue 1964 Gotham Book Mart. 1964, 1963 (Box 11:*1)
    Cover photograph by Carl Van Vechten-also Introduction, "More laurels for Our Gertrude." At the back: "Reprinted from our Catalogue No. 36." Carries a piece by James Laughlin, IV entitled: "About Bilignin and Literature and the G.B.M." Above "More Laurels for Our Gertrude," Its author inscribed: *"For Bino (See note number 3) with Much Love from Carlo November 16, 1963 New York."
  - Gotham Book Mart Catalogue No. 36 1937 (Box 11:2)
    Introduction by James Laughlin, IV, Entitled: "About Bilignin and Literature and the G.B.M." (See above.)
  - Playbill--Off Broadway, Inc.-for the New York Premi貥 of Yes IS For a Very Young Man1949 (Box 11:3)
    Directed by Lamont Johnson. Opening night June 6, 1949. On back "A Word to You from Gertrude Stein.
  - French publishers' handout for Am=eacute;ricains d'Am=eacute;rique par Gertrude Stein. Juillet 1933.1933 (Box 11:4)
  - Columbia University Libraries, An Exhibition of the Writings of Gertruded Stein.No Year (Box 11:5)
    Lent by the Courtesy of Yale University Library .... Tuesday, April 29, at 8.30p.m. Low Memorial Library. [Printed Card.]
  - Typed folded flyer: An Exhibition of the Writings of Gertrude Stein (1874-1946). Stewart Memorial Library, Coe College. 1947? (Box 11:6)
  - Card in Envelope. Another of the two above. Booth Library, Newtown, CT. 1947? (Box 11:7)
  - ITEMS OF SPECIAL INTEREST AND POTENTIAL VALUE
  - Cheque drawn on Mechanics & Merchants Bank, Richmond, VA., made out to, and *endorsed by, Gertrude Stein. For $200 from Mark Lutz. Dated: February 9, 1935. 1935 (Box 11:*8)
  - Have They Attacked Mary. He Giggled. 1917 (Box 11:9)
    (A Political Caricature), by Gertrude Stein. Limited, and Unabridged, Edition (200 copies) Of a Poem which first appeared in Vanity Fair (June, 1917). Inscribed on flyfleaf: "For Mark, 'A great many settlers have mercy,' I like what I say to Mark, and what he does. You are proud. I am proud of my [illegible] courage' [?] Paper 7 [?] For Mark Gtde. Stn."
  - Looking At Pictures With Gertrude Stein No Date (Box 11:*10)
    Tiny booklet with facsimile [?] signature on flyleaf. Six leaves; three photographs.
  - Envelope addressed to Mark Lutz, and postmarked New York, January 3, 1935. Enclosed is a photograph, taken at Bilignin, of Mark Lutz with Gertrude Stein and her two dogs. 1935 (Box 11:11)
  - Admission Card for "Plays and What They Are." No Date (Box 11:12)
    A Lecture by Miss Gertrude Stein. Inscribed:"For Mark. Gtde."
  - Portrait of Mabel Dodge at the Villa Curonia, by Gertrude Stein. 1912[?] (Box 11:13)
    Privately printed, bound with wallpaper, and published in Italy.
  - Postcard from Belley, Ain, France-addressed by Alice Toklas (to ensure delivery, no doubt)-from Gertrude Stein to Mark Lutz. Post-marked: October 23, 1936. 1936 (Box 11:14)
  - Two almost identical 'Christmas Cards'-[not sent] from Fania Marinoff & Carl Van Vechten. 1948 (Box 11:15(a) & (b))
    Pale blue, pink & pale green. Two (hitherto unpublished) Poems, by Gertrude Stein. Copyright 1948 by Alice B. Toklas. Limited (205 copies of this First Edition) edition. Banyan Press.15(a) No. 4, inscribed: "Dearest Baby The Banyan Press [illegible] kept Nos. 1,2, & 3 and you have the rare No. 4.With all my love.Carlo December 1948." 15(b) is like unto it namely this: *"Dear Marco, The Banyan [illegible] have [ sic] Nos. 1, 2, 3, Fania has No. 4, Alice No. 5, I No. 6 and you have the rare No. 7. Love Carlo!"
  - Sir Francis Rose, by Gertrude Stein. 1934 (Box 11:*16)
    Elaborate exhibition catalogue of the artist's works. At the Marie Harriman Gallery, 61-63 East 57th Street, New York City. December 7 to 29, 1934. Inscribed:*"For Mark, ... [Illegible] Gtde, Stn."
  - Exhibition brochure 1951 (Box 11:17)
    Pictures for a Picture: Of Gertrude Stein as a Collector and Writer on Art and Artists. Yale University Gallery, February-March, 1951, and The Baltimore Museum of Art, March-April, 1951.
  - Large manilla envelope containing various playbills, programs, exhibition cataloges, etc.. Various (Box 11:18)
  - Large manilla envelope containing newpaper cutouts and clippings of book reviews of Stein's works Various, 1934 (Box 11:*19)
    One is the whole edition of Vol. XI No. 17 (Saturday, November 10, 1934) of The Saturday Review of Literature, which bore on the front page and p. 2, an article by Gertrude Stein, "Plays and Landscapes"-("a condensed form of the lecture on plays she planned to deliver during her current American trip." [Editor's note]) Inscribed above the title: *"For Mark who will [illegible] it all ... Gdte."
- Gertrude Stein
  - Town & Country, Vol. 101, No. 4296, (May 1947). May 1947 (Box 12:1)
    pp. 80-81: "The Mother of Us All," by Saul Steinberg-with drawings to fit the score of the opera of that name which Gertrude Stein helped to create and produce.
  - Harper's Bazaar, No. 2825 (May 1947) May 1947 (Box 12:2)
    "The Mother of Us All," pp. 144-145. An excerpt from the new opera by Gertrude Stein and Virgil Thomson. On the extreme Left of this two-page spread is a photograph of Gertrude, on a summer holiday, singing an old song she loves; "The Trail of the Lonesome Pine."
  - Vanity Fair, Vol. 43, No. 5 (January 1935) January 1935 (Box 12:3)
    P. 25: "Impossible Interview-Gracie Allen versus Gertrude Stein," by Miguel Covarrubias. Large coloured caricature by that artist.
  - The Bystander, Vol. CXXXIV, No. 1743 (May 12, 1937). May 12, 1937 (Box 12:4)
    pp. 262-263: two-page spread with six photographs of the ballet "A Wedding Bouquet," a Berners-Stein-Ashton production at Sadlers Wells.
  - The Yale University Library Gazette, Vol. 27, No. 2 (October 1952). October 1952 (Box 12:*5)
    "Carl Van Vechten's Gertrude Stein," by Donald Gallup, pp. 77-86. This is a fascinating and highly informative piece inasmuch as it gives a detached account of how and when the two met; who was instrumental in bringing about the meeting, & c., & c.. At the top of page 77 is inscribed: *"For Marco with love from Carlo. Nov. 11, 1952. New York."
  - The Yale University Library Gazette, Vol. 28, No.2 (January 1954). January 1954 (Box 12:5)
    Article by Donald Gallup entitled, "Gertrude Stein and The Atlantic," pp. 109-128.
  - Bulletin of Bibliography and Dramatic Index, Vol. 17, No. 10 (January-April 1943). January-April 1943 (Box 12:6(a) & 6(b))
    Coupled with the subsequent issue of the above, Vol. 18, No. 1 (May-August 1943) completes Parts I & II May-August 1943 of "Gertrude Stein: A Check List."
  - The Black and Blue Jay, Vol. VI, No. 5, (April 1926). April 1926 (Box 12:7)
    John Hopkins University, Baltimore. One page (16) devoted to our Gertrude. Two boxed insets: One of which is a facsimile of the lady's handwriting. The other is a sixteen-line poem[?] entitled: "One Has Not Lost One's Marguerite."
  - Two acid-eroded issues of an avante garde French publication-printed in Holland-called Transition [ed. Eugene Jolas] No. 15 (Winter Number-February 1929); and No. ? 1934-1935. February 1929, 1934-1935 (Box 12:*8(a) & 8(b))
    The former carries on pp. 47-58 a "Bibliography of Gertrude Stein," over the title page of which the Stein inscribed: *"For Mark, Gtde." 8(b) which also boasts a big piece on James Joyce's Work in Progress -[later to become Finnegan's Wake]- includes a pamphlet, called: The Testimony against Gertrude Stein,
- Gertrude Stein Materials. Magazines Containing Articles by
  - Harper's Bazaar, No. 2856 (December 1949) pp. 93, 148, 154, 156 & 157: "Raoul Dufy," by Gertrude Stein. [Written in Plain English!] December 1949 (Box 13:1)
  - Vanity Fair, Vol. 43, No. 1 (September 1934) September 1934 (Box 13:2)
    "And Now," by Gertrude Stein, pp. 35 & 65. Largely dealing with her success it is "written" -as the Editor puts it-"in a not too difficult style." Page 13, 'The Editor's Uneasy Chair' prepares readers for the anticipated visit of Stein and Toklas to the United States.
  - Hearst's International, Combined with Cosmopolitan, Vol. XCVIII, No. 2 (February 1935) "I Came and Here I Am," 1935 (Box 13:*3)
    pp. 18, 19, 167, & 168. Photographs on opening spread, below which, inscribed in green ink: *"For Mark in Babylon[?] and[?] [illegible] Gtde."
    **Editor's note in box states that "orthodox punctuation has been inserted to make it easier to read."
  - Issues of The Atlantic1933-1937 (Box 13:4)
    Magazines for years 1933, 1934, and 1937 featuring pieces by and about Gerty Stein. In the 1933 issues the Autobiography of Alice B. Toklas is serialized.
  - The Book League Monthly, Vol. 1, No. 1 (November 1928) 1928 (Box 13:5)